Guide to the Papers of Paul Wendorf ALBA.120
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Paul Wendorf Papers
February 1937-September 1938
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Wendorf, Paul
ALBA.120
0.5 Linear Feet (1 box)
Paul Wendorf (1912?-1938) fought with the Abraham Lincoln Brigade in the Spanish Civil War and died during an aerial attack in the Sierra Pandols, one month prior to the withdrawal of the International Brigades. This collection consists chiefly of letters written by Wendorf to his wife during his 19 months in Spain. Also included are newspaper clippings and ephemera.
Provenance
The Paul Wendorf Papers was donated to Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives in October 1980 by Charles Nusser. This collection came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of ALBA collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Historical/Biographical Note
Paul Wendorf graduated with a B.A. from Columbia University, where he majored in history and economics, in 1932. In 1933, while working as an organizer for the American League against War and Fascism, he joined the Communist Party. Over the course of the next three years, he worked as an activist and labor organizer in New York City, first for a white-collar municipal workers' union, and subsequently as a coordinator of welfare and relief for the unemployed. He married Leona Grossman and soon after enlisted in the Abraham Lincoln Brigade to fight on behalf of the Republican forces in Spain. He sailed on the S.S. Paris on February 6, 1937 and served in Spain from February 1937 until August 1938.
He fought in the battle at the Jarama front from March to June 1937, and in the Brunete offensive from July until August 1937. He was appointed in September 1937 to the Historical Commission in Albacete and, under the supervision of Sandor Voros, participated in writing the history of the 15th International Brigade and the American battalions. He also contributed articles to the Brigade's newspaper the Volunteer for Liberty. In January of 1938 he was charged, along with Carl Geiser, with organizing a school for political commissars. A bout of rheumatism and subsequent hospitalization prevented him from carrying out this assignment, and by March, he was returned to active service. He took part in the Ebro offensive, the Brigade's final conflict, and crossed the Ebro with the Lincoln Brigade late in July. On August 18, 1938, Wendorf was killed during an aerial attack in the Sierra Pandols, only one month prior to the withdrawal of the International Brigades. In 1939 Charles Nusser, a fellow Lincoln Brigade veteran and Wendorf's friend, married Leona Grossman Wendorf.
Scope and Content Note
Series I, Correspondence, contains Wendorf's outgoing correspondence during his 19 months in Spain from February 1937 to September 1938. His letters are addressed chiefly to his wife Leona (referred to by the endearment "Mug") and chronicle his time in Spain beginning with his voyage to France, through to his final days of battle in the hills of the Sierra Pandols. Wendorf is a keen observer of life in the trenches as well as the towns and streets of Spain. His letters offer information on his military career and the activities of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade; the progress of the Fascist forces; the political climate in Spain; his hospitalization and convalescence; and his critical views on the press, both mainstream and radical. Most notable are his full descriptions of the Lincoln Brigade's crossing of the Ebro, which appear in his final two letters (8/2/1938 and 8/8/1938). This series also includes two letters written to union associate Sherry Schulman, and to his friend Charles Nusser, who returned to the United States in February 1938.
Series II, Subject Files, includes several unaddressed postcards including one with a political slogan, and a Republican Christmas greeting from the Red Cross. Also here are mementos including a peseta note and a dried flower; news clippings, including one from the Manchester Guardian that appears to contain the text of a letter written by Wendorf; and a copy of the Volunteer for Liberty with an article that Wendorf wrote shortly before his death.
Arrangement
Series one is arranged chronologically. Series two is arranged alphabetically.
The files are grouped into 2 series:
Missing Title
I. Correspondence
II. Subject Files
Jarama River Valley (Spain); Spain -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Periodicals.; Ebro River, Battle of the, Spain, 1938.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Campaigns.; Personal papers.; Correspondence.; Articles.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Belchite (Spain) -- History -- Siege, 1937.; Wendorf, Paul; Voros, Sandor.; Geiser, Carl; Nusser, Charles; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Brigada Internacional, XV; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Abraham Lincoln Battalion
- Series I: Correspondence
  - Outgoing, Feb 1937-Mar 1937 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Outgoing, Apr 1937-May 1937 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Outgoing, Jun 1937-Jul 1937 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Outgoing, Aug 1937-Sep 1937 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Outgoing, Oct 1937-Nov 1937 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Outgoing, Dec 1937 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Outgoing, Jan 1938 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Outgoing, Feb 1938 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Outgoing, Mar 1938 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Outgoing, Apr 1938-May 1938 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Outgoing, Jun 1938 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Outgoing, Jul 1938 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Outgoing, Aug 1938 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Series II: Subject Files
  - Cards, Dec 1937, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Ibarruri, Dolores: Portrait by Paul Wendorf, 1937 (Box Shared Tamiment MSXOS002, Folder 1)
  - Mementos: dried flower, peseta, weight card, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - News Clippings, Aug 1938-Dec 1938 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Volunteer for Liberty, Aug 26, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 17)